Guide to the Hart, Budd, and Nestell Family Papers 1804–1955 MS 3127
New-York Historical Society
Hart, Budd, and Nestell family papers
1804–1955
New-York Historical Society
Hart family
Nestell (Family)
MS 3127
1 Linear feet (in 1 record carton).
A small collection of 19th and early 20th-century deeds, wills, estate inventories, legal papers, and portrait photographs documenting the intermarried Hart, Budd, and Nestell families of Westchester County, New York, and New York City. The collection includes two maps and a series of 1912 photographs of properties at Avalon, on Santa Catalina Island, Los Angeles, California, many of which were lost to fire in 1915.
Arrangement
The collection is organized alphabetically by surname or topic in 38 folders.
Biographical / Historical
(All names underlined below are represented by documents in the present collection.)
The family documented here descends chiefly from Monmouth Hart (1689–1761), of Westchester County, New York, and his wife, Sarah Ogden. Among the children of Monmouth and Sarah (Ogden) Hart was a son, Joseph Hart (circa 1726/7–1807). By his marriage to Elizabeth Gidney, Joseph was the father of another Joseph Hart (1757–1836). The younger Joseph married Tamar Budd, a daughter of Joseph Budd, and among their children was a son, Henry Hart, who married Esther Horton. The children of Henry and Esther (Horton) Hart included John Horton Hart (1819–1886), Joseph Budd Hart (1825–1878), Henry Azariah Hart (1832–1865), and George Washington Hart (1837–1896).
New York City merchant Joseph Budd Hart—not to be confused with his uncle, fellow merchant Joseph B. Hart (1796–1887)—married Emma Selina Nestell (1834–1907), a daughter of John Joachim Nestell (1809–1885) and Jane Ann Elizabeth Schultz. Together Joseph Budd and Emma S. (Nestell) Hart had four children: Irene Nestell (Hart) Collord (1860–1950), George Henry Hart (1861–1867), Charles Henry Hart (1867–1940), and Emma Josephine (Hart) Sheridan (1869–1916).
Joseph Budd Hart died in 1878, leaving substantial real estate holdings. His will appointed as executors his brother, George Washington Hart, his widow, Emma, and Emma's brother, John Jay Nestell (1840–1917). The latter took control of the estate's affairs, but was eventually charged with failing to account for about $600,000 of it. Hart's heirs claimed Nestell misused the funds to speculate on recreational properties at Avalon, on Santa Catalina Island, in Los Angeles, California, for his personal gain (hence the maps and photographs in Folders 23–25).
This note draws largely from genealogical data supplied by the donor found in Folder 1. See, also, "Accused of Failing to Render Account" in the Los Angeles Herald, Saturday 15 August 1908, p. 12, and "Estate $600,000 Short. Referee Charges Speculation with J. B. Hart Property" in the New York Tribune, Saturday 14 May 1910, p. 7.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Charles Centerfit Hart, December 2018 (accession no. MS-2019-007).
Scope and Contents
The bulk of the collection contains deeds, wills, estate inventories, legal papers, and portrait photographs of members of the intermarried Hart, Budd, and Nestell families, dating from the early 19th through early 20th-centuries. The family held significant amounts of real property in New York City, and files for those properties contain instruments such as quitclaim deeds, building permits, proposals, specifications, and the occasional blueprint. The properties at Avalon, on Santa Catalina Island, in Los Angeles, California, are marked on two maps (1912 and undated) and documented by two series of photographs: one taken in 1912, the other in 1915 after a fire had destroyed half of Avalon's buildings.
Avalon (Calif.); Harlem (New York, N.Y.); New York (N.Y.); Westchester County (N.Y.); Real property -- New York (State) -- New York.; Real property -- New York (State) -- Orange County; Deeds.; Estate inventories.; Mortgages.; Photographs.; Wills.; Hart family; Nestell (Family)
- [Genealogical data and collection information], [2018] (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Budd, Joseph. Estate, 1826 July 21 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Collord, Irene Nestell (Hart) (1860–1950). Estate, 1947 October 14 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Hart family. Photographs, circa 1860–1900 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Scope and Contents
  Includes carte-de-visite and cabinet card photographs of
  Emma S. Hart
  Esther Horton Hart (1794–1875)
  George Hart (1861–1867)
  George W. Hart
  George & Anne Hart
  Henry Azariah Hart (1832–1865)
  John Horton Hart (1819–1886)
  Joseph Budd Hart (1825–1878)
  William Horton Hart
  Two unidentified
- Hart, Charles Henry (1867–1940). Photographs, circa 1870–1895 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Hart, Emma Selina (Nestell) (1834–1907). Estate, 1907–1910 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Hart, Henry (1787–1848). Assignments, bonds, mortgages, releases, 1834–1845 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Hart, Henry (1787–1848). Will, 1841 April 27 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Hart, Henry (1787–1848). Estate inventory (Eastchester, Westchester Co., N.Y.), 1848 June (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Hart, Jane (Barker). Transfer of mortgage to John G. Horton, 1849 August 1 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Hart, Joseph (circa 1726/7–1807). Will (Bedford, Westchester Co., N.Y.), 1804/1807 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Will dated December 28, 1804; proved April 10, 1807.
- Hart, Joseph (circa 1757–1836). Deed, 1810 January 25 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Hart, Joseph (circa 1757–1836). Estate, 1834–1838 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Hart, Joseph Budd (1825–1878). Notebook, 1849–circa 1985 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Notebook originally the property of Joseph Budd Hart (1825–1878), containing genealogical data, family bible records, and later contributions by Hart's descendants. Many pages blank.
- Hart, Joseph Budd (1825–1878). School rewards of merit (4), [1830s] (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Hart, Joseph Budd (1825–1878). Estate (2 folders), circa 1875–1910 (Box 1, Folder 16–17)
  "Papers on Judgement against John Jay Nestell as executor under the Last Will & Testament of Joseph Budd Hart."
- Hewer, William and Martha. Release to William Ward, 1844 January 25 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Nestell family. Photographs, circa 1860–1900 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  Edward Victor Nestell (1871– )
  John Joachim Nestell (1809–1885)
  Raymond Jay Nestell (1877–1968)
- Nestell, John Joachim (1809–1885). Miscellaneous, 1849, 1854 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Nestell, Schultz, and Coger families. Vital statistics, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Notebook [blank], [circa 1899] (Box 1, Folder 22)
  Promotional pocket-sized notebook issued by E. S. Higgins Carpet Co., 41 Union Square West, New York.
- Real estate. Avalon, Santa Catalina Island, Los Angeles, California (3 folders), 1911–1912, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 23–25)
  Maps and photographs of properties owned/managed by John Jay Nestell (1840–1917), purportedly as executor for the estate of his brother-in-law, Joseph Budd Hart (1825–1878). The maps (2), labeled "Map showing portions of Town of Avalon, Catalina Island" (undated) and "Map of portion of the Town of Avalon, Santa Catalina Island, Los Angeles Co., California" (March 11, 1912), are marked to indicate the following properties, each of which is recorded by an accompanying photograph (spread across Folders 23 and 24):
  Bijou Apartments
  Blake Bonnie Cottage [or Blink Bonnie Cottage]
  Brownie Cottage
  Buena Vista Cottage
  Campus Virginia
  Firenze Apartments
  Floral Camp No. 1
  Floral Camp No. 2
  Isabella House
  Loraine Apartments
  Pacific Hotel
  Rosemary Cottages (Nestell Place)
  Savoie
  Sea Breeze Cottage
  Tio Juan Houses
  Touraine Apartments
  For further details, see the transcript of a "Journal kept by Charles Henry Hart, 199 Lenox Avenue, New York, New York, of a business trip to Denver, Colorado and Catalina Island, California, February 26, 1912 to March 23, 1912" in Folder 1.
  Folder 25 holds photographs depicting the aftermath of the fire of November 29, 1915 that destroyed half of Avalon's buildings, including, from the list above, the Bijou, Brownie, Firenze, Loraine, Pacific Hotel, Rosemary, Savoie, Sea Breeze, Tio Juan, and Touraine.
- Real estate. New York, N.Y. Attorney Street, no. 105, 1837, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Real estate. New York, N.Y. East 3rd Street, no. 38, 1942 April 20 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Real estate. New York, N.Y. East 124th Street, no. [31?], 1861, 1867, 1884 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Real estate. New York, N.Y. East 124th Street, nos. 15-21, and East 125th Street, nos. 16-24, circa 1926–1955 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Real estate. New York, N.Y. East 125th Street, no. 24, 1875, 1899, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Real estate. New York, N.Y. East 128th Street, no. 157-159, 1884–1905 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Real estate. New York, N.Y. Lenox Avenue, no. 199, 1897 July 20 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Real estate. New York, N.Y. Ridge Street, no. 41, 1843 December 30 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Real estate. New York, N.Y. St. Mark's Place, no. 65-67, 1849–1851 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Real estate. New York, N.Y. West 125th Street, no. 76 (2 folders), 1908–1909 (Box 1, Folder 35–36)
- Real estate. Orange County, N.Y., 1818, 1819 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  Two deeds for property in the Drowned Lands, today known as the Black Dirt Region, of Orange County, New York: Wm. Townsend, Isaac Townsend, et al., to John Hildreth (October 19, 1818), and John Hildreth to Robert Wardell (January 16, 1819).
- The Sun [newspaper], 1834 March 11 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  According to the donor (see copy of letter dated December 4, 2018 in Folder 1), this single issue of The Sun, published at New York, was found inside an old Hart family bible that his father, John Budd Hart (1918–1982), had brought to Birmingham, Alabama, to be re-bound. The donor had the newspaper framed under glass, with both sides visible. That is how it came to the New-York Historical Society. The frame was discarded on March 5, 2020.